Finding Aid for the Carey McWilliams Collection of Material About Mary Hunter Austin LSC.0278
UCLA Library Special Collections
Carey McWilliams collection of material about Mary Hunter Austin
1868-1934
UCLA Library Special Collections
LSC.0278
0.5 Linear Feet (1 box)
Mary Hunter Austin (1868-1934) was an author who published thirty-one books and many short stories, essays, and poems. The collection consists of letters, manuscripts, articles, clippings, and ephemera by and about Mary Austin. The bulk of the collection is made up of letters to Carey McWilliams and magazine and newspaper clippings.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942303403606533
Biography
Mary Hunter Austin was born September 9, 1868 in Carlinville, Illinois; she was an American author who published thirty-one books and many short stories, essays, and poems; writings on the American Southwest include The Flock (1906), Lost Borders (1909), The Land of Journeys' Ending (1924), The Land of Little Rain (1903), and an autobiography titled Earth Horizon (1932); died, August 1934.
Carey McWilliams was born December 13, 1905 in Steamboat Springs, Colorado; J.D., University of Southern California; attorney, Black, Hammack & McWilliams, Los Angeles, 1927-38; chief of Division of Immigration and Housing, California State Governor, 1938-42; contributing editor, associate editor, and editorial director, The Nation, 1945-55; editor, The Nation, 1955-1975; some of his books include: Ambrose Bierce, a Biography (1929), Factories in the Field: The Story of Migratory Farm Labor in California (1939), Ill Fares the Land: Migrants And Migratory Labor In The United States (1942), Brothers Under the Skin (1943); Prejudice: Japanese-Americans, Symbol of Racial Intolerance (1944), Southern California Country: An Island on the Land (1946), A Mask for Privilege: Anti-Semitism in America (1948), The Education of Carey McWilliams (1979); died of cancer, June 27, 1980 in New York, New York.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of letters, manuscripts, articles, clippings, and ephemera by and about California author Mary Austin. The bulk of the collection is made up of letters to Carey McWilliams (series 1) and magazine and newspaper clippings (series 4). Manuscripts include two of Austin's film scenarios which were never produced, Bride of the Sun and The Flock. Three photographs and negatives which were part of the original collection were transferred to the Photographic Collection (Collection 99) at the Department of Special Collections, UCLA.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Letters to Carey McWilliams.
Manuscripts.
Material about Mary Austin.
Magazine and newspaper clippings.
Letters to various persons.
Related Material
Mary Austin Papers. Available at The Huntington Library, San Marino, California.
Authors, American -- Archives.; Austin, Mary, 1868-1934--Archives.; Austin, Mary; Austin, Mary, 1868-1934--Correspondence.; McWilliams, Carey -- Correspondence
- 1. Letters to Carey McWilliams, 1905-, (69 pieces)
  - 4 holograph letters signed. (Box 1)
  - 58 typescript letters signed. (Box 1)
  - 1 typescript letter. (Box 1)
  - 5 typescript letters signed by secretary. (Box 1)
  - 1 telegram. (Box 1)
- 2. Manuscripts and Scenarios
  General note
  (See also II-C, Indian Arts and Crafts)
  - A. Bride of the Sun,., 1929; 6 holograph leaves in the author's hands. quarto. (Box 1)
  - B. The Flock,., 1932; Typescript copy. 12 leaves, quarto. (Box 1)
  - 1 leaf of typescript on talent and genius prepared by Mrs. Austin. (Box 1)
    In folder with The Flock.
  - Indian Arts and Crafts. Santa Fe,., 1931; 19pp. (17 leaves) 21.5 × 28 cm. Typescript. (Box 1)
  - Unpublished letter from Mary Austin to Paul Kellogg, editor of the Survey Graphic. Santa Fe, February 5, 1932. 1 item (1 leaf) Typescript (signed)., 19pp. (17 leaves) 21.5 × 28 cm. Typescript. (Box 1)
- 3. Material about Mary Austin, (11 pieces)
  - 1. Typescript carbon copy of letter of Carey McWilliams to Mr. Wynn, the publisher, containing twenty eight answers to Mr. Wynn's questions concerning this collection of Mary Austin material. (Box 1)
  - 2. Typescript copy of book review of Austin's The Ford., 7pp. quarto. (Box 1)
  - 3. Carbon copy of typescript manuscript of Mr. McWilliams's article on Mary Austin and her work written at the request of Harry Carr for publication in the Los Angeles Times., 4pp. quarto. (Box 1)
  - 4. Two miscellaneous letters & clippings. (Box 1)
- 4. Magazine and Newspaper Clippings, (46 items)
  - 1. Thirty six clippings from The Nation, Saturday Review of Literature, Saturday Night, Brentano's Book Chat, etc. of Mary Austin's poetry, essays, book reviews and articles about her. (Box 1)
  - 2. Ten newspaper clippings about the death and character of Mrs. Austin. (Box 1)
- 5. Letters to Various Persons, (3 pieces)
  - 1. Letter to Miss Williams. Independence, California,., October 27; 3pp. (with typescript). (Box 1)
  - 2. Photocopy of letter to Charles Augustus Keeler in Huntington Library. Los Angeles, California, n.d. (Box 1)
  - 3. Letter to Henry James Forman. Carmel, California,., September 17, 1918; 4pp. Original typescript. (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    This letter was published as a keepsake, Mary Austin on the art of writing: a letter to Henry James Forman, with an introduction by James E. Phillips, by The Friends of the UCLA Library, Los Angeles, 1961. Printed by Grant Dahlstrom at the Castle Press, Pasadena, September 1961. (6pp. Wrappers, included with the letter).